# Curriculum Vitae – Ingo P. Waldmann

### PERSONAL INFORMATION

Waldmann, Ingo Peter ORCID: 0000-0002-4205-5267 Date of birth: 18th July 1986 Nationality: German URL: ingowaldmann.com

### **RESEARCH FOCUS**

My expertise is in Bayesian modelling and information theory applied to exoplanetary atmospheric measurements. In particular, I have pioneered techniques for the data analysis of very low signal observations and the de-correlation of non-linear, correlated systems. These include the use of supervised and unsupervised machine learning, deep neural networks for pattern recognition, non-linear component separation and information geometry to map high-dimensional probability spaces. My work finds application both in the data analysis of weak signals and the modelling of complex atmospheres of extrasolar planets.

#### **EDUCATION**

2009 - 2012 PhD in Astrophysics

Dept. Physics & Astronomy, University College London, UK

Advisors: Prof. Tinetti, Dr. Fossey

My thesis entitled "Of 'Cocktail Parties' and Exoplanets" pioneered the data analysis of exoplanetary time series and spectra using unsupervised machine learning algorithms. I finished my PhD within 2.5 years (1.5 years ahead of schedule)

Awards: The 'Jon Darius Memorial Prize' for best annual PhD thesis of the Faculty.

2005 - 2009 M.Sci. & B.Sci in Astropysics & Planetary Sciences,

> Mathematical & Physical Science Faculty, Dept. of Natural Science, University College London, UK

Degree awarded: First Class Honours

Awards: 1) Brian Duff Memorial Prize for best Master thesis in Physics, 2) Natural Science Award for best final year performance in the Mathematical and Physical Sciences.

### **CURRENT POSITION**

2014 - present Senior Research Associate & Lecturer at UCL

Outline: Science and Project lead on de-correlation of observational data using machine-learning; Project lead on radiative transfer inverse retrieval modelling. Funding body: UK Space Agency, European Research Council (ExoLights/ExoMol)

### PREVIOUS POSITIONS

2014 NASA Fellow (NPP) at NASA-Jet Propulsion Laboratory

> Outline: Chief developer of data analysis framework for the NASA/FINESSE space mission and the JPL-NMT/NESSI exoplanet survey. I decided to decline this fellowship in favour of my work for the European Space Agency – EChO space mission concept.

Funding body: NASA

2012 - 2014Research Associate at UCL

> Outline: Key developer & science lead of the European Space Agency's EChO spacemission concept's end-to-end mission simulator.

Funding body: UK Space Agency

### **FELLOWSHIPS & AWARDS**

- NASA Postdoctoral Fellowship (2014)
- Jon Darius Memorial Prize for Outstanding Postgraduate Research: awarded for the best PhD thesis in Physics.
- Brian Duff Memorial Prize for best Masters Thesis in Physics: awarded for the best Masters thesis in Physics.
- STFC Postgraduate Studenship
- Natural Science Award for best final year performance

### SUPERVISION OF GRADUATE AND POST-GRADUATE STUDENTS

- 2012 2016 Marco Rocchetto (PhD, Dept. Physics & Astronomy, UCL)
- 2014 2017 Angelos Tsiaras (PhD, Dept. Physics & Astronomy, UCL)
- 2016 2019 Tiziano Tsiaras & Mario Damiano (PhD, Dept. Physics & Astronomy, UCL)
- 2013 2016 Giuseppe Morello (co-supervised PhD, Dept. Physics & Astronomy, UCL)
- 2012 2015 Ryan Varley co-supervised PhD, Dept. Physics & Astronomy, UCL)
- 2012 present Supervised 5 Masters project (2 of which currently)

### **CURRENT PROJECT LEADS:**

- Data analysis group leader of ESA/M4 Ariel space-mission concept.
- Data analysis group leader of UK Twinkle space-mission concept.
- Chief UK contact for atmospheric modelling for the JWST/MIRI consortium.
- Chief UK contact for atmospheric modelling for the US/UK EXCITE high-altitude balloon consortium
- Chief-designer of the data analysis framework for the JPL-NMT/NESSI exoplanet survey instrument

### **RECENT PRESS RELEASES:**

"Dreaming of Atmospheres", Royal Astronomical Society - UCL 2016 press release; e.g.:

- Over 30 news articles in 4+ languages.
- <a href="http://www.dailymail.co.uk/sciencetech/article-3666639/Meet-Robert-alien-hunting-AI-Smart-software-scour-exoplanets-signs-life.html">http://www.dailymail.co.uk/sciencetech/article-3666639/Meet-Robert-alien-hunting-AI-Smart-software-scour-exoplanets-signs-life.html</a>
- <a href="https://blogs.nvidia.com/blog/2016/08/01/deep-learning-will-speed-search-for-extraterrestrial-life">https://blogs.nvidia.com/blog/2016/08/01/deep-learning-will-speed-search-for-extraterrestrial-life</a>
- https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/06/160627214628.htm
- http://www.popsci.com/how-scientists-will-use-artificial-intelligence-to-find-aliens

European Space Agency - UCL 2016 press release:

- Over 200 news articles in 12+ languages; e.g.:
- <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/bridaineparnell/2016/02/17/super-earths-atmosphere-detected-for-the-first-time-and-its-dry-hot-and-poisonous/#172a04591879">http://www.forbes.com/sites/bridaineparnell/2016/02/17/super-earths-atmosphere-detected-for-the-first-time-and-its-dry-hot-and-poisonous/#172a04591879</a>
- http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/science-environment-35586936
- <a href="http://www.seeker.com/hubble-studies-super-earth-atmosphere-for-first-time-1770881884.html">http://www.seeker.com/hubble-studies-super-earth-atmosphere-for-first-time-1770881884.html</a>
- https://www.spacetelescope.org/news/heic1603/

### **TEACHING ACTIVITIES**

2016	Lecturer at the Como Summer School on Exoplanets, Como, Italy
2015 - 2017	Course convenor & Lecturer: Astronomy Dissertations (PHAS1514/2523) – UCL,
	UK
2012 - 2015	Course convenor & Lecturer: Exoplanets and Spectroscopy (PHAS2525) - UCL,
	UK
2014	Lecturer at the International ATIC winter school for Atmospheric Physics, Lethbridge,
	Canada
2011 - 2012	Lecturer at the European Research Course on Atmospheres (ERCA) Uni Grenoble

 $<sup>&</sup>quot;Detection \ of \ an \ Atmosphere \ Around \ the \ Super-Earth \ 55 \ Cancri \ e",$ 

### France

### ORGANISATION OF SCIENTIFIC MEETINGS

- Organiser of the James Webb Space Telescope MIRI consortium atmospheric modelling group, 20 participants, hosted at UCL.
- 2012 2016 Co-organiser of ARIEL and EChO consortium meetings, over 15 in various EU countries, between 30 150 participants.

### INSTITUTIONAL RESPONSIBILITIES

- 2012 2016 Graduate Student Advisor, of 6 PhD level and 5 Masters level students, UCL, UK
  2012 2015 Organiser of Departmental Astrophysics Seminars, UCL, UK
  2016 2018 Member of Faculty Large Scale Computing Committee; Astrophysics PDRA representative, UCL, UK
- 2012 2015 Member of a Staff/Student Departmental Committee; PDRA representative, UCL, UK

### **COMMISSIONS OF TRUST**

2016	Science and Technology Funding Council (STFC) University Grant referee, UK
2014 - present	William Herschel Telescope proposal referee, UK
2012 - present	Referee for the following journals: Astrophysical Journal Astronomical Journal

2012 – present Referee for the following journals: Astrophysical Journal, Astronomical Journal, Astronomy & Astrophysics, ICARUS, Proceedings of the Royal Society

# MEMBERSHIPS OF SCIENTIFIC SOCIETIES

- 2007 present Fellow of the Royal Astronomical Society
- 2009 present Member of the American Astronomical Society
- 2009 present Member of the European Geophysical Union
- 2007 present Fellow of the British Astronomical Association

## **MAJOR COLLABORATIONS**

- James Webb Space Telescope MIRI atmospheric modelling consortium, UK representative
- European Space Agency ARIEL consortium member and Data analysis lead
- NASA/JPL FINESSE consortium, atmospheric modelling UK representative
- European Space Agency EChO consortium member and mission end-to-end modelling lead

### **LANGUAGES**

German (native), English (bilingual), Spanish (proficient), French (beginner)

#### **TALKS & SEMINARS:**

- 45+ talks at international conferences, lectures and seminars (21 invited) from 2010 present
- International ATIC winter school for Atmospheric Physics (PhD/PDRA Level) lecturer (Lethbridge, Canada). Topics: 1) Machine learning in spectroscopic data analysis, 2) atmospheric spectroscopy 2014
- European Research Course on Atmospheres (PhD/PDRA level) lecturer (Grenoble, France). Topics: 1) Atmospheric spectroscopy of exoplanets, 2) Low and high-resolution data analysis of ground and space based exoplanetary observations 2011 & 2012
- Chaired sessions at various international conferences and meetings (e.g. Committee on Space Research/COSPAR, American Astronomical Society – DPS, Europlanet, Royal Astronomical Society National Astronomy Meeting, European Space Agency – EChO and ARIEL meetings)

### Selected Invited Talks and Seminars

- Re-Works conference on machine learning (Amsterdam, Netherlands) shed. June 2017
- Uni. Bern Seminar (Bern, Switzerland) Nov. 2016
- Uni. Arizona Seminar (Tuscon, USA) Oct. 2016
- Como Summer School (Como, Italy) June 2016
- Harvard CfA Seminar (Boston, USA) Apr. 2016
- Laboratoire d'Astrophysique de Bordeaux Seminar (Bordeaux, France) Mar. 2016
- Centre Energie Atomique (CEA) seminar (Paris, France) Feb. 2016
- Institute d'Astrophysique Paris colloquium (Paris, France) 2015
- NASA/Goddard Space Center seminar (Washington, USA) 2015
- ExoMol conference, keynote talk (London, UK) 2015
- Royal Astronomical Society: Twinkle workshop (London, UK) 2015
- Remote Sensing of Exoplanets winter school (Lethbridge, Canada; two lectures) 2014
- IAP seminar (Paris, France) 2014
- COSPAR invited talk (Bangkok, Thailand) 2013
- Rutherford Appleton Laboratories seminar (Oxfordshire, UK) 2013
- Max Planck Institute for Astronomy (Heidelberg, Germany) 2013
- Centre for Inverse Processes (London, UK) 2013
- Gaia meeting (Turin) 2012
- Queen Mary University Physics seminar 2012
- European Research Course on Atmospheres (Grenoble, France; two lectures) 2012
- European Research Course on Atmospheres (Grenoble, France; one lecture) 2011
- UCL Astrophysics Seminar (London, UK) 2011
- IEEC invited seminar (Barcelona) 2010